这是重型猎鹰在肯尼迪航天中心LC-39A起飞的声音
This is the sound of the Falcon Heavy, lifting off from pad 39A at the Kennedy Space centre
27台梅林发动机起飞时产生了550万磅的推力（约2500吨）
With 27 Merlin engines firing to produce 5 and a half million pounds of thrust
可以说是很吵了
it's fair to say, it’s pretty loud
对于这种力量的火箭，如此大的声音已经可以
For rockets with this much power, the sound energy produced by the engines can actually
对火箭自身和周围建筑造成危害了
be very damaging to the rocket itself as well as the surrounding buildings
本期视频我们将了解NASA为了减少噪声危害采取的办法
In this video we’re going to look at the method that NASA uses to reduce some of the reduce some of the sound damage
也将了解毛子为了解决此问题采取的另一种独特办法
We’re also going to look at the unique way that the Russian’s deal with this problem
当火箭起飞的时候，发动机的炽热尾气进入火焰导流槽
When a rocket lifts off from the launch pad, the engine exhausts fire hot gas into the flame trench
除了来自发动机的大量的热能
Along with the incredible heat energy coming from the engines
还有很多声音的能量
there is also a lot of sound energy
据NASA说，土星五号起飞的时候会产生220分贝的噪声
According to NASA, the Saturn 5 produced a sound level of around 220 decibels during lift-off
如果你离火箭足够近，你就不是耳膜穿孔那么简单了
If you were in close proximity to the engines, it wouldn’t just rupture your eardrums
你就直接被震死了
it would kill you
在航天飞机首飞任务STS-1中
During the launch of the first Space Shuttle flight STS-1
发动机产生的噪声过大
the sound energy produced by the engines was powerful enough
导致航天飞机表面的防热瓦被部分破坏
to damage some of the protective thermal tiles on the Shuttle's hull
尽管当时NASA已经使用了噪声抑制系统
Although NASA used sound suppression systems in the past
航天飞机受噪声影响的风险依然很大
the risk of damaging the rocket or putting the crew in danger was higher for the shuttle
因为其外形特殊且隔热瓦很脆弱
due to its unique shape and sensitive heat shield
为了防止飞机受损，也为了不把成员置身于危险中
To avoid damaging the vehicle or putting the crew in danger
NASA使用了一种更加有效的噪声抑制系统
NASA solved this problem by implementing a more effective sound suppression system
发射架旁边有个高高的水塔
This consists of a large water tower at the launch site
在发射时会将超过一百万磅（四百多吨）的水倾泻在发射台上
which dumps over 1 million lbs of water onto the launch pad in just 40 seconds
当声波遇到水后会被空气中的水汽吸收并加热
As the sound waves meet the water, they are absorbed by bubbles of air which contract and heat up
于是声波的能量就变成了热能
turning the sound energy into heat energy
除了这么多往里倒的水
Along with this enormous spray of water
NASA还在航天飞机固推下面使用水袋来进一步减少噪声
NASA also used “water bags” at the base of the SRB’s to further dampen the shock waves
这些巨大的尼龙袋，每个一英尺宽一英尺深
These were large nylon bags - each about one foot wide and one foot deep
装满水，横跨整个固推的喷火口
filled with water and stretched across the SRB flame holes
喷水加水袋一起，让航天飞机起飞的噪声强度
Together, these two systems were able to reduce the sound level of the Space Shuttle
从195分贝降低到142分贝，相当于战斗机起飞的声音
from 195 decibels to a more respectable 142, the equivalent of a jet taking off
尽管看到喷水系统工作有点困难
Although it can be difficult to see the water deluge system in action
但在喷水测试中我们则能清楚感受到这水量有多大
it’s during a sound suppression test that we really get a sense of just how much water is used
向发射台倾泻这么多的水不仅会保护火箭和附近的建筑免遭噪声破坏
Dumping this much water onto the launch pad not only protects the rocket and nearby buildings from intense shock waves
它还能扑灭火箭尾焰造成的任何火灾
it also stops any fires that might be caused by the rockets exhaust
直到今天，NASA还在很多主发射场上使用类似的喷水系统
To this day, NASA still uses a very similar water deluge system at all of their main launch sites
而毛子那边，方法则非常“毛子”
The Russians on the other hand, have a different approach
由于毛子的很多联盟号火箭是从哈萨克斯坦的拜卡努尔发射场发射的
Since a lot of the Russian Soyuz rockets launch from Baikanour in Kazakhstan
而那气温最低能有零下四十度，水刚喷出去就结冰了
where the temperatures can be as low as -40 degrees in the winter, a water deluge system would freeze up instantly
这还喷个毛线
making it completely useless
所以他们干脆使用非常非常大的尾焰导流槽
Their solution is to simply suspend the rocket over a much larger flame trench
使得很少的冲击波会伤到或反弹回火箭箭体
This means that there is very little in the way for the shock waves to damage or reflect back onto the rocket
所以虽然搞火箭要面对很多复杂的工程难题
So although rocket science deals with some of the most complex engineering challenges
但发现有些问题可以用如此简单粗暴的办法解决还是很有趣的
it’s interesting to see that some problems can be solved with very simple solutions
如果大家还有什么问题，欢迎在评论区讨论
If you have any questions be sure to leave them in the comments below
字幕翻译给虫
记得关注点赞投币收藏分享转发哦
非常感谢充电的同学们！
喜欢视频的欢迎关注YouTube频道“Primal Space”，赞助链接见下
If you enjoyed this video and would like to contribute to Primal Space, please visit Patreon.com/PrimalSpace
到50个赞助会抽土星五号乐高哦
where we will be doing a giveaway of a Saturn V Lego set, once we reach 50 Patrons
所以记得关注，多多讨论，一起学习和太空有关的知识
So make sure you’re subscribed so you can join the discussion as we continue to learn more about all things space
那么感谢观看，下期视频见啦
Thank you very much for watching and I’ll see you in the next video